ERIC GRIMSON: So now we've seen arithmetic expressions.
We've seen giving names to those.
We've seen how we can combine those together using names and
places where we would use values.
We can start doing some simple computations.
But those are all dealing with scalar objects, numbers.
Let's talk briefly about other kinds of objects.
We'll come back to them later on, but we want to see what we
can do here.
So non-scalar objects are compound things, things whose
proportions or components we can get at.
We'll see a lot of these throughout the course of this
subject, but the simplest one to start with are what are
called strings, or objects that have a
type str for string.
And these are literally just sequences of characters that
are all concatenated together.
So how do we write them?
Well literals of this type can be written either by putting
them inside of a single quote or putting them inside of
double quotes.
And so if I go to my Python shell, for example, we can see
that we can put things within a single quote.
And that gives us that string back.
By the way, we can give names to those things.
So we can say, what's the value of foo, and, in fact, we
can look at the type and we'll see that it gives us back
something of type string or str.
We can now similarly put things inside of double
quotes, which is convenient, for example, if we want to put
things with gaps or spaces in between them.
And, by the way, we can also put quotes around numbers.
So this is a string.
And just to see that, let's ask for the type of that.
The type of that sequence of characters, numeral one,
numeral two, numeral three, inside of the
double quotes is a string.
And that is different than the type of the number itself
which is in int.
So we can put together strings.
If we can put them together we'd like to be able to do
things with them.
And I want to show you some examples of those.
So we can provide different operations on strings.
Now some of these maybe a little surprising.
So let's walk through them.
The first one is we can ask for taking the string a and
multiplying it by the number three.
And that may sound strange.
But what it gives us is a string with three copies of
a's stuck together.
Or, if you like, I could do it with a slightly more
complicated string.
And it literally is just concatenating or copying those
versions of those strings together.
We can put two strings together using addition to
give us this concatenated string of a and b.
And we can, of course, also concatenate the other strings
if we want to make sure that they are
converted into strings.
So we can take a number, convert it to a string and
concatenate that together gives us the string a123.
These are just different ways of dealing with strings and
putting them together.
It seems a little odd that we're using operators that
don't normally deal with numbers.
And this is an instance of what we call operator
overloading.
In which what we are doing here, here, here, is we are
using the same operator to do different things.
If we give them numbers it'll do one thing.
If we give them a number and a string in the case of
multiplication it will do something different.
If we give them two strings it will do something different.
So we're letting the operator use the type of the object to
decide what the right operation is to do.
The last one we show here is that given we say we now have
a non-scalar object we need to know how many portions are
there inside of it.
And for that there's a built-in Python function
called len for length.
And if I want to ask for the length of a particular string
it gives me back that answer.
So I now have compound objects that I can do things with.
Well obviously one of the things I'd like to do is not
just put them together.
I'd like to get parts out of them.
So that leads to the interesting question of how do
I get out elements of a compound object like a string.
And here I want to show two examples.
The first one is we can do what's called the indexing.
And let me show you an instance of this.
If I give the string 'abc'.
Notice the single quotes around it so that is a string.
And in square brackets are braces after it I give it an
integer, like 0, it's going to give me out the element of the
string corresponding to that index.
Now how does it do this?
Well it starts--
well, if you want to think of it this way of
counting from 0.
So there's the string.
The zeroth element is that one.
And it will return that value.
Similarly if I say from the string 'abc' give me the
second element it starts at 0,1,2
there's the second element.
And it returns that string.
Now you have to be careful.
If I ask for the third element.
Remember, I start counting at 0.
There's 0, 1, 2.
The third element, oh, there isn't one.
And we get out an error.
And we can seen this over here.
If I, for example, just type it into Python.
I can say give me the string 'abc.' And I'll take, in this
case, the first element.
And that will give me b.
Because I start at 0 and go to 1.
Now I can also though go backwards.
So if I have a string 'abc' and I give it in square
brackets or braces a negative number, it basically starts at
0 and then counts backwards to minus 1 and then to minus 2.
So that minus 1 index will return as the c.
So it basically starts at the back end and counts backward.
So we get out components of strings which is good.
Now sometimes we'll want to get out not just a single
element, we'll want to get out a substring of a string.
And for that we have a technique called slicing.
So we have a string called s, then this expression here
where we have two expressions, a start and an end that are
both integers or their values are integers that denotes the
substring that starts at the index pointed to by start and
stops just before the index pointed to by end.
So just to see that.
If I again take my string 'abc' and I say give me
everything starting at one and stopping before the third
index it returns for me the string bc.
We're going to come back to doing things with strings
later on, but we wanted to let you see that given compound or
non-scalar objects like strings, not only can we
combine together but we can also get out pieces of them.
Either individual elements or subcomponents of them.
And we'll use that as we start doing more interesting
things moving on.